<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The answer of Ferdinando Lord Fairfax to a declaration of William Earle of Newcastle, touching a late vvarrant issued by the Lo: Fairfax, dated 2. February. 1642. As also, the Lord Fairfax's willingnesse to decide the controversie with the said Earle of New-castle in a fayre field.</title>
            <author>Fairfax, Ferdinando Fairfax, Baron, 1584-1648.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84610</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F111</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E91_28</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4479</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872689</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872689</idno>
            <idno type="VID">125135</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84610)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 125135)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 16:E91[28])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The answer of Ferdinando Lord Fairfax to a declaration of William Earle of Newcastle, touching a late vvarrant issued by the Lo: Fairfax, dated 2. February. 1642. As also, the Lord Fairfax's willingnesse to decide the controversie with the said Earle of New-castle in a fayre field.</title>
                  <author>Fairfax, Ferdinando Fairfax, Baron, 1584-1648.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the appointment of Fernando Lord Fairfax: at London for Iohn Franke, and are to be sold at his shop next door to the Kings-head Taverne in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>March 3. 1642 [i.e. 1643]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Newcastle, William Cavendish, --  Duke of, 1592-1676. --  Declaration of the Earle of Newcastle in answer of six groundlesse aspersions cast upon him by the Lord Fairefax.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:125135:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ANSWER OF <hi>Ferdinando</hi> Lord <hi>FAIRFAX</hi> TO A DECLARATION OF <hi>William</hi> EARLE of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> TOUCHING, A late VVarrant iſſued by the Lo: <hi>Fairfax,</hi> dated 2. <hi>February.</hi> 1642.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AS ALSO,</hi> The Lord <hi>Fairfax's</hi> willingneſſe to decide the controverſie with the ſaid Earle of <hi>NEW-CASTLE</hi> in a fayre Field.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed by the appointment of Ferdinando</hi> Lord <hi>Fairfax:</hi> AT LONDON For <hi>Iohn Franke,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop next door to the Kings-head Taverne in <hi>Fleet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctreet.</hi> March 3. 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb facs="tcp:125135:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:125135:2"/>
            <head>The Anſwer of <hi>Fardinando</hi> Lord <hi>Fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fax,</hi> to a Declaration of <hi>VVilliam</hi> Earl of <hi>NEW-CASTLE, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is come to my hands a printed Paper, Entituled, a Declaration of the Earle of Newcaſtle, wherein he aſſumes an inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to anſwer and vindicate himſelf from the ſix aſperſions pretended to be caſt on him in my Warrant, dated the ſecond of Feb: 1642. I muſt confeſſe there wants no flouriſh of art nor lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage in the Declaration to deceive an inconſiderate multitude, though to any judicious Reader, it will ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhow that the Earl of Newcaſtle is galled and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with the Warrant, then able to clear himſelfe of thoſe juſt charges layd upon him in it; ſo that I might well ſpare the paines of replying to it, if I had not a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to undeceive the miſguided opinions of that multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, of which a great part do either lead or follow his Lordſhip in the deſtructive Counſells that have endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered the ruine of the Religion and flouriſhing State of this Kingdom: And therefore though I want a Preſſe to divulge my conceptions, yet I ſhall make uſe of my pen to ſatisfie all impartiall judgements that every point
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:125135:3"/>in the ground of that. Warrant is moſt evidently true, wherein I ſhall obſerve his Lordſhips order, and begin with the defence of the firſt and ſecond charges. That his Lordſhip hath contrary to the Lawes of the Land, raiſed a great Army of Papiſts and other Malignants. I hope no man is, or ought to be ignorant, that by a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Statute declarative of the Law it is enacted, that the free ſubjects of <hi>England</hi> ſhall not be preſſ'd to ſerve in the wars without their own conſent in Parliament, and by judgement lately paſſed in Parliament, and executed, it is deemed to be high Treaſon, to levy war, or to Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell the King to levy war within this Kingdom, in ſuch manner as the Earl of Newcaſtle hath done, and by ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry other Statutes it is provided, that Recuſants ſhall neither bear arms nor be ſuffered to have them in their houſes, as inconſiſtent with the ſafety and peace of the Kingdom, and of the Religion therein eſtabliſhed, and yet nevertheleſſe the Earl of Newcaſtle hath contrary to the known law of the Land preſſed and conſtrayned the ſubjects to ſerve in this war, and many extremities have been by his order put upon thoſe that refuſed: and hath raiſed and armed the Recuſants, and with their Forces leavied a War in the land, and all this pretended to be done under pretence (if any man have faith enough to believe it) for defence of the Proteſtant Religion, and the laws of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the third charge, that with this Army unlawfully raiſed, he hath invaded this county, it is too true, and ſo plain, as his Lordſhip ſeeks colours and arguments, rather to juſtifie then deny it, and therefore I ſhall not need to ſay much to juſtifie the truth of the charges, onely I ſhall deſire the Reader to obſerve this, that where his Lordſhip ſaith, the Kings Forces cannot make invaſion in his own Dominions, it may be juſtly ſuſpected, that the Kings
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:125135:3"/>Name and Authority in this particular, are miſguided and miſapplyed, ſeeing His Majeſty hath often and ſolemnly promiſed, not to make this County the ſeat of a War, and therefore withdrew his own Forces from thence; and this ſuſpicion receives more ſtrength by the Earl of <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtles</hi> own frequent confeſſions, that he undertook this invaſion upon the earneſt intreaty of ſome of the Nobility and Gentry of this County.</p>
            <p>For the fourth charge, the Earl of Newcaſtle doth not deny it, but he indeavours to extenuate the fact by allegation, that he hath killed nor deſtroyed none of the religious Proteſtant Subjects, but ſuch as take up armes againſt him and his aſſiſtants, which are already confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by him to be partly Papiſts, and all now proved to be unlawfully raiſed and employed, and whoſoever will conſider the attempts of that Army at <hi>Tadcaſter</hi> and <hi>Bradford,</hi> and their oppreſſions at <hi>Leedes, York,</hi> and other places of the County, where they have practiſed all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Tyranny upon mens perſons, and carved what they need or pleaſe out of other mens eſtates without payment, will eaſily conclude that it is both more Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianlike, &amp; more lawfull &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> coming a loyall Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, to dye in his own defence, then to ſuffer both bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſoul to be inflamed by the violence and practiſe of ſuch enemies. In this fourth Article, the Earl of New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtle takes liberty of extravagant expreſſions to infuſe into the vulgar, two of his opinions: Firſt, that I and thoſe with me take up Armes without lawfull warrant from the King; Secondly, that if I had performed that agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which he alleadgeth I was bound unto in honour and juſtice, all the blood ſpilt in this cauſe had been ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Both the charges, as moſt part of the Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſeem by the cited authority, to have more in them of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:125135:4"/>the Jeſuit than of the States-man or Lawyer, for the Earl of Newcaſtle cannot be ignorant, that I and thoſe aſſiſting me, act nothing which is not warranted, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by the Kings greateſt and moſt infallible Councell the Parliament, by whoſe advice the King either is, or ought to be ruled, and by whoſe powerfull and prudent counſells and aſſiſtance, this Monarchy hath been ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for many hundred of yeers, and my prayers are that it may ſo ſubſiſt to the worlds end. And for the ſecond it is not unknowne to all men curious to know the truth, that though the agreement which the Earl of Newcaſtle ſeemes to point at, was not concluded according to the inſtructions given by me, yet for avoyding of blood I obſerved it in all points, untill the adverſe party had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringed it in four ſeverall materiall branches, (which by divers Letters I repreſented to them) though never could obtain reparation, and untill my own houſe grew unſafe for me, the adverſe party ſending me menacing Letters, and demanding reſtitution of priſoners, as if no agreement at all had been made: So that I cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive how it ſhould be thought that I broke the agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, unleſſe my Lord of Newcaſtle would have me ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to perform all covenants, and allow the adverſe party a Popiſh diſpenſation, giving them liberty to violate all, and be tyed by no bonds nor agreements.</p>
            <p>And in this place I may properly take opportunity to tell the Reader, that four or five dayes before the making of that agreement, Sir <hi>John Savile</hi> coming to meet me at <hi>Leeds,</hi> to view, and order the Trained bands according to the Ordinance of Parliament, and bringing ſome few of his Tenants and neighbours with him to ſhew their armes, they were layed in wait for, and ſet upon by the Troopes commanded by Sir <hi>Thomas Glemham</hi> and Sir
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:125135:4"/>
               <hi>John Goodricke,</hi> and other forces who ſlew three of the company, and made Sir <hi>John Savile</hi> and all the reſt pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners: And this was the firſt guiltleſſe blood ſhed in this County ſince the King left theſe parts, and at whoſe hands it will be required the world may judge.</p>
            <p>For the firſt charge excepted againſt by the Earle of Newcaſtle, the Goales at <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Pomfret</hi> can witneſſe with me, that I have not wronged his Lordſhip, for in them he hath impriſoned the Miniſters of <hi>Knaresborough, Newton, Beningborough, Edlinton,</hi> and ſundry other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and he hath baniſhed from their Cures, Maſter <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> the Miniſter of Ayworth, M. <hi>Tod</hi> of the new Church of Leeds, M. <hi>Nolſon</hi> of Holebecke, Mr. <hi>Haukesworth</hi> of Hunſlet, M. <hi>Headcoat</hi> of Ardſley, and the Miniſters of ſundry other places, being all of them men of blameleſſe doctrine and converſation, and allowed by God and man to hold their Cures, and then what authority the Earl of Newcaſtle hath to impriſon or drive them from it, is to me unknown.</p>
            <p>The ſixt charge touching plunders done by his men he doth not deny, but takes no notice of the particulars, which indeed are infinite, but he ſpends much labour to aſperſe me with the ſame crime, of which I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent the Country will acquit me, who know full well how I deteſt ſuch Tyranny, and how carefull I have been to ſuppreſſe the inſolence of the ſouldiers that way, and to cauſe reparation where I found any ſuch acts have been done by the forces really under my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and I wiſh the Earl of Newcaſtle would do the like, that ſo all mens purſes that are filled by ſuch unjuſt gains, might be left as empty as when they began to practiſe thoſe deteſtable courſes.</p>
            <p>And to conclude, the Declaration quarrells with my
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:125135:5"/>warrant, that talkes of driving him out of the Country which truely I thinke all men that affect Religion &amp; Peace have great cauſe to deſire.</p>
            <p>And therefore without following the rules of <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gaule,</hi> or the Knight of the Sun, which the language of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Declaration ſeemes to affect in appointing pitch'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> tells, I ſhould moſt willingly deſigne both time, and place, to decide the controverſie in a fair field, if the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of the Country could be determined in one day or if the adverſaries could be conſtrayned to obſerve <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> appointments. But both theſe being either impoſſible, or improbable, All I can ſay in anſwer of the concluſion is, that whereſoever I find an opportunity to offer or tell to his Lordſhip, I ſhall take it for a great honour that I may do him that ſervice; and I hope all men that have obſerved the reſolution of my Army, at <hi>tadcaſter</hi> and <hi>Leeds,</hi> will eaſily beleeve me.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
